Finding Aid for Emerson R. Boyles papers, 1879-1911 and 1931-1960
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Emerson R. Boyles papers 1879-1911, 1931-1960
Boyles, Emerson R., 1881-1960.
1 oversize folders
6 linear feet
85840 Aa 2; Ac
Charlotte, Michigan, attorney, legal advisor to Governors Frank Fitzgerald and Luren Dickinson and justice of the Michigan Supreme Court. Correspondence, newspaper clippings and other materials on Michigan politics, the Republican Party, and his association with Governor Dickinson; scrapbook, 1885-1889, compiled by Fred A. Pennington; account book, 1904-1905; day book, 1941; log book, 1942, of Beaver Island cabin; and miscellaneous notebooks and photograph albums.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Henry Crouse (donor no. 3806 ) and came to the library in 1961.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Emerson R. Boyles was born in Chester Township, Eaton County, June 29, 1881. He graduated from the University of Michigan Law School in 1903, then entered the practice of law in Charlotte. He was elected prosecuting attorney, 1912-1916; probate judge of Eaton County, 1921-1927. He resigned to become Deputy Attorney General with Attorney General William W. Potter and served in that capacity for six years. He was appointed member of Michigan Public Utilities Commission, 1935-1936, then became legal adviser to Governor Fitzgerald and Governor Dickinson, who in August 1940 appointed Boyles to fill out the term of Supreme Court Justice William W. Potter. He was elected to fill the vacancy, November 5, 1940, and re-elected in 1943 and 1950. He died November 30, 1960.
The Emerson Boyles papers consist of correspondence, newspaper clippings and other materials on Michigan politics, the Republican Party, and his association with Governor Dickinson; a scrapbook, 1885-1889, compiled by Fred A. Pennington; account book, 1904-1905; day book, 1941; log book, 1942, of Beaver Island cabin; and miscellaneous notebooks and photograph albums. The collection has been arranged into three series: Correspondence and other papers; Miscellaneous personal and family; and Photographs.
Subjects:
American Liberty League.; Beaver Island (Mich.); Boyles, Emerson R., 1881-1960.; Charlotte (Mich.); Crusade for Freedom.; Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.; Depressions--1929--Michigan.; Japanese Americans.; Judges--Michigan.; Lapeer Mutual Fire Insurance Company.; Lawyers--Michigan.; Missionaries--Congo (Democratic Republic); Order of Patrick Henry.; African Americans--Michigan.; Starr Commonwealth for Boys.; Strang, James Jesse, 1813-1856.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; World War, 1939-1945.; Patton, George S. (George Smith), 1885-1945.; Prisons--Michigan.; Protestant Reformed Churches of America.; Republican Party (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Michigan. Judges' Retirement Board.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Boyles, Emerson R., 1881-1960.; Boyles family.; Camping.; Children.; Delton (Mich.); Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.; Fishing--Michigan.; Holidays.; Horses.; Hunting--Michigan.; Ice fishing.; Ice skating.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Photography.; Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.; Wall Lake (Mich.); Winter.
Contributors:
Bingay, Malcolm Wallace, 1884-; Blodgett, John Wood, 1860-1951.; Bonisteel, Roscoe O. (Roscoe Osmond), b. 1888.; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Bushnell, George E. (George Edward), 1887-1965.; Butzel, Henry M. (Henry Magnus), 1871-1963; Chandler, Bert D.; Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Ford, Edsel, 1893-1943.; Hoffman, Paul G. (Paul Gray), 1891-1974.; Johansen, August E. (August Edgar), 1905-1995; Kellogg, W. K. (Will Keith), 1860-1951.; Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.; Knight, John Shively, 1894-1981.; Lindemer, Lawrence B.; McKay, Frank D., 1883-; Miriani, Louis C.; Mott, Charles Stewart, 1875-1973.; North, Walter Harper, 1871-1952.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.; Smith, William Parkhurst, 1897-; Starr, Floyd Elliot, 1883-1980.; Starr, Raymond Wesley, 1888-1968.; Stason, E. Blythe (Edwin Blythe), 1891-1972.; Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Wiest, Howard, 1864-1945.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Wilson, Charles Erwin, 1890-1961.; Yntema, Hessel E.; Ziegler, Charles M., 1888-1959.; Pennington, Fred A.; Reid, Neil E., 1871-; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Sharpe, Edward M., 1887-; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence and other papers
  The bulk of the Correspondence and other papers series covers the years 1939 to 1960 when Boyles served as legal advisor to Governors Frank D. Fitzgerald and Luren D. Dickinson (1939-1940), and as justice of Michigan's Supreme Court (1940-1956). Boyles' correspondence includes both letters received and copies of his own letters. While much of the collection is composed of family letters, there is a large body of letters, memoranda, clippings, and other materials pertaining to state and national politics, the Michigan Supreme Court and legal practice in Michigan.
  - 1931-June 1942, 33 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1942-September 1947, 56 folders (Box 2)
  - October 1947-March 1952, 52 folders (Box 3)
  - April 1952-June 1956, 49 folders (Box 4)
  - July 1956-December 1960 undated, 49 folders (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous personal and family
  The Miscellaneous personal and family series contains earlier materials of other Boyles family members, including a scrapbook from the 1880s concerning events in Charlotte, Michigan.
  - Certificates (Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook1885-1889 relating to events in Charlotte, Michigan, compiled by Fred A. Pennington, 1885-1889 (Box 6)
    (includes photographs)
  - Account book 1904-1905 (Box 6)
  - Daybook 1941 (Box 6)
  - Logbook 1942 of Beaver Island cabin (Box 6)
  - Diaries, etc. (little content), 4 volumes (Box 6)
  - Family and other miscellanea, 3 folders (Box 6)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes portraits of Boyles, members of his family, the Supreme Court, and Governors Luren D. Dickinson and Kim Sigler. There are also photographs of hunting and fishing trips, ice fishing, vacations at Wall Lake, Michigan, cottages, and horses.
  - Camping (Box 6)
  - Luren D. Dickinson (Box 6)
  - Groups, including E.R. Boyles (Box 6)
  - Groups, not including E.R. Boyles (Box 6)
  - Michigan Supreme Court (Box 6)
    (see also oversize folder)
  - Portraits of E.R. Boyles (Box 6)
  - Photograph album 1914-1915 of vacation scenes (Box 6)
  - Kim Sigler (Box 6)
  - Family and personal postcards (Box 6)
  - Michigan Supreme Court (Folder 1)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Bingay, Malcolm Wallace, 1884-
May 6, 1940, June 12, 1942
Blodgett, John Wood, 1860-1951
Dec. 10, 1941, Jan. 2, 1942, Apr. 1, 1942
Bonisteel, Roscoe O. (Roscoe Osmond), b. 1888.
Mar. 26, 1951
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.
Jan. 13, 1940, Mar. 23, 1954
Bushnell, George E. (George Edward), 1887-1965.
1940-1950
Butzel, Henry Magnus, 1871-
1941-1951
Chandler, Bert D.
1941-1944
Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.
1939-1942
Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.
Sept. 2, 1948
Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.
Dec. 21, 1936, Mar. 1939 [clippings]
Ford, Edsel, 1893-1943.
Feb. 8, 1943
Hoffman, Paul G. (Paul Gray), 1891-1974.
Nov. 20, 1951
Johanson, August Edgar, 1905-
Nov. 6, 1956
Kellogg, W. K. (Will Keith), 1860-1951.
Sept. 5, 1939
Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.
Apr. 10, 1941, Mar. 25, 1943, May 24, 1943, Sept. 22, 1943, Feb. 5, 1945
Knight, John Shively, 1894-1981.
Nov. 6, 1942
Lindemer, Lawrence B.
Mar. 7, 1960
McKay, Frank D., 1883-
Feb. 15, 1940, Dec. 25, 1940, Dec. 25, 1941, Dec. 25, 1942
Miriani, Louis C.
July 24, 1940, Nov. 7, 1951
Mott, Charles Stewart, 1875-1973.
July 9, 1957
North, Walter Harper, 1871-1952.
July 9, 1941
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860
1943-1945
Reid, Neil E., 1871-
1945-1946
Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.
Mar. 11, 1940 [To Luren D. Dickinson]
Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.
Dec. 4, 1939 [autograph value only]
Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-
Apr. 11, 1952
Sharpe, Edward M., 1887-
1942-1951
Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.
Aug. 14, 1940, Dec. 22, 1941, Mar. 19, 1947, Sept. 11, 1947, July 13, 1948
Smith, William Parkhurst, 1897-
1940-1960
Starr, Floyd Elliot, 1883-1980.
1940-1960
Starr, Raymond Wesley, 1888-1968.
July 14, 1943-, July 13, 1945
Stason, E. Blythe (Edwin Blythe), 1891-1972.
May 8, 1950, Sept, 30, 1950, Mar. 9, 1953, June 4, 1954, May 12, 1960
Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-
June 23, 1952, July 12, 1952, June 22, 1953, Aug. 31, 1953, Feb. 15, 1954
Vandenberg, Arthur Hendrick, 1884-1951.
Nov. 26, 1943, Aug. 1939-Mar. 1940 and Mar. 19, 1946 [On "Vandenberg Movement for Michigan"]
Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
Dec. 28, 1940
Wiest, Howard M., 1864-1945.
Aug. 30, 1940
Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-
Nov. 23, 1956
Wilson, Charles Ervin, 1890-1961.
Mar. 18, 1949
Yntema, Hessel E.
1951-1955
Ziegler, Charles M., 1888-1959.
1951-1955